I'm going to talk a little bit about where technology's going.
سأتحدث قليلاً ٌإلى أين تتجه التكنولوجيا.
And often technology comes to us,
وغالبا ما تصلنا التكنولوجيا،
we're surprised by what it brings.
ونتفاجأ بما يصحبها.
But there's actually a large aspect of technology
ولكن في الواقع يوجد جانب كبير من التكنولوجيا
that's much more predictable,
الذي يمكننا التنبؤ به إلى حد كبير،
and that's because technological systems of all sorts have leanings,
وهذا بسبب أن الأنظمة التكنولوجية من كل الأنواع لديها ميول
they have urgencies,
لديها حاجات ملحة،
they have tendencies.
لديها اتجاهات معينة.
And those tendencies are derived from the very nature of the physics,
وتستمد تلك الاتجاهات من الطبيعة الفيزيائية،
chemistry of wires and switches and electrons,
من كيمياء الأسلاك والمفاتيح والإلكترونات،
and they will make reoccurring patterns again and again.
وسوف ينتج عنها أنماط معينة تتكرر مرة تلو الأخرى.
And so those patterns produce these tendencies, these leanings.
وتلك الأنماط ينتج عنها تلك الميول والاتجاهات.
You can almost think of it as sort of like gravity.
يمكنك أن تتصورها كنوع من الجاذبية.
Imagine raindrops falling into a valley.
تخيل قطرات المطر تنهمر في وادي.
The actual path of a raindrop as it goes down the valley
المسار الحقيقي الذي ستسلكه قطرات المطر إلى قعر الوادي
is unpredictable.
لا يمكن التنبؤ به.
We cannot see where it's going,
لا يمكننا رؤيتها إلى أين تتجه،
but the general direction is very inevitable:
ولكن الاتجاه العام هو أمر لا مفر منه:
it's downward.
نحو الأسفل.
And so these baked-in tendencies and urgencies
لذا فإن هذه الميول والاتجاهات المضمنة
in technological systems
في الأنظمة التكنولوجية
give us a sense of where things are going at the large form.
يمكننا أن تعطينا فكرة عامة إلى أين نتجه بشكل عام.
So in a large sense,
وبشكل عام،
I would say that telephones were inevitable,
يمكنني القول إن الهاتف كان أمراً حتمياً،
but the iPhone was not.
ولكن الآيفون لم يكن كذلك.
The Internet was inevitable,
الإنترنت كان أمراً حتمياً،
but Twitter was not.
ولكن تويتر لم يكن كذلك.
So we have many ongoing tendencies right now,
لذا لدينا اتجاهات عامة تحدث الآن،
and I think one of the chief among them
وأعتقد أن أحد أهم هذه الاتجاهات
is this tendency to make things smarter and smarter.
هو الاتجاه لجعل الأشياء أكثر وأكثر ذكاء.
I call it cognifying -- cognification --
أسميه الإدراك الاصطناعي
also known as artificial intelligence, or AI.
كما يعرف بالذكاء الاصطناعي.
And I think that's going to be one of the most influential developments
وأعتقد أن هذا سيكون من أكثر التطورات تأثيراً
and trends and directions and drives in our society in the next 20 years.
على ميول وتوجهات مجتمعنا خلال ٢٠ سنة المقبلة.
So, of course, it's already here.
وبالطبع هي توجد معنا الآن.
We already have AI,
لدينا حاليا الذكاء الإصطناعي
and often it works in the background,
وغالبا ما تكون تعمل خلف الكواليس،
in the back offices of hospitals,
في الآلات الخليفة في المستشفيات،
where it's used to diagnose X-rays better than a human doctor.
حيث تستخدم لتشخيص صور الأشعة بشكل أفضل من التشخيص البشري.
It's in legal offices,
كما يوجد في المكاتب القانونية
where it's used to go through legal evidence
حيث تستخدم لمراجعة الأدلة القانونية الموجودة
better than a human paralawyer.
أفضل من أي محام بشري.
It's used to fly the plane that you came here with.
تستخدم لتحليق الطائرة التي جاءت بك اليوم.
Human pilots only flew it seven to eight minutes,
قام الطيارون البشريون بالطيران لمدة ٧ أو ٨ دقائق،
the rest of the time the AI was driving.
قام الذكاء الاصطناعي بكل المهام الباقية
And of course, in Netflix and Amazon,
وبالطبع يوجد في نيتفلكس وأمازون،
it's in the background, making those recommendations.
حيث يعمل في الخلفية لتقديم الاقتراحات لك.
That's what we have today.
هذا ما لدينا اليوم.
And we have an example, of course, in a more front-facing aspect of it,
كما لدينا مثال لأحدها يعمل بصورة مباشرة أكثر لنا،
with the win of the AlphaGo, who beat the world's greatest Go champion.
حيث تغلب برنامج "ألفاجو" على أشهر بطل عالمي في "جو".
But it's more than that.
لكن يوجد المزيد لهذا.
If you play a video game, you're playing against an AI.
إن لعبت بلعبة فيديو، فأنت تلعب ضد ذكاء اصطناعي.
But recently, Google taught their AI
قامت جوجل مؤخرا بتعليم ذكائهم الاصطناعي
to actually learn how to play video games.
كيفية تعلم لعب ألعاب الفيديو.
Again, teaching video games was already done,
ومرة أخرى، تعليم ألعاب الفيديو أمر تم القيام به سابقا،
but learning how to play a video game is another step.
لكن تعلم كيفية لعب ألعاب الفيديو هي خطوة أخرى.
That's artificial smartness.
وذلك هو الذكاء الاصطناعي.
What we're doing is taking this artificial smartness
وما نقوم به هو أخذ ذلك الذكاء الاصطناعي
and we're making it smarter and smarter.
ونجعله أكثر فأكثر ذكاء.
There are three aspects to this general trend
وتوجد ثلاثة جوانب لهذا الاتجاه العام
that I think are underappreciated;
أعتقد أنها لم تلقى التقدير اللازم،
I think we would understand AI a lot better
وأعتقد أننا سنفهم الذكاء الاصطناعي بصورة أفضل
if we understood these three things.
إن نحن فهمنا تلك الجوانب الثلاثة.
I think these things also would help us embrace AI,
أعتقد أن هذه الأشياء ستساعدنا في تقبل الذكاء الاصطناعي،
because it's only by embracing it that we actually can steer it.
لأننا لن نتمكن من توجيهه إلا أن قمنا بتقبله.
We can actually steer the specifics by embracing the larger trend.
يمكننا فعلا توجيه التفاصيل إن قمنا بتقبل الاتجاه الأكبر.
So let me talk about those three different aspects.
لذا سأتحدث عن تلك الجوانب الثلاث المختلفة.
The first one is: our own intelligence has a very poor understanding
الأول هو: أن ذكائنا لديه فهم ضعيف جدا
of what intelligence is.
لما هو الذكاء.
We tend to think of intelligence as a single dimension,
نميل للتفكير أن الذكاء يوجد في بعد واحد فقط،
that it's kind of like a note that gets louder and louder.
كما الحال في النغمة الموسيقية التي يرتفع صوتها تدريجيا.
It starts like with IQ measurement.
كما يحصل في قياس معدل الذكاء.
It starts with maybe a simple low IQ in a rat or mouse,
حيث تبدأ غالبا بقياس بسيط منخفض لفأر مثلا،
and maybe there's more in a chimpanzee,
ثم يرتفع أكثر قليلا مع شمبانزي،
and then maybe there's more in a stupid person,
ثم شخص لديه ذكاء محدود،
and then maybe an average person like myself,
ثم شخص عادي مثلي أنا،
and then maybe a genius.
ثم لدى شخص نابغة
And this single IQ intelligence is getting greater and greater.
وهو مقياس ذكاء يكبر أكثر فأكثر.
That's completely wrong.
هذا خاطئ تماما.
That's not what intelligence is -- not what human intelligence is, anyway.
هذه ليست حال الذكاء، على الأقل الذكاء البشري.
It's much more like a symphony of different notes,
الأمر أشبه بالسمفونية الموسيقية التي تحتوي على نغمات متعددة،
and each of these notes is played on a different instrument of cognition.
وكل من هذه النغمات تعزف على آلة مختلفة من الإدراك.
There are many types of intelligences in our own minds.
توجد في عقولنا أنواع مختلفة من الذكاء.
We have deductive reasoning,
لدينا الاستدلال الاستنتاجي،
we have emotional intelligence,
لدينا الذكاء العاطفي،
we have spatial intelligence;
لدينا الذكاء الحيزي،
we have maybe 100 different types that are all grouped together,
لدينا حولي 100 نوع مختلف موجودون مع بعضهم البعض،
and they vary in different strengths with different people.
وتختلف درجة قوة كل منهم من شخص إلى آخر.
And of course, if we go to animals, they also have another basket --
وإن نظرنا إلى الحيوانات، فسنجد مجموعة أخرى
another symphony of different kinds of intelligences,
أنواع أخرى من الذكاء مشكلة سمفونية فيما بينها،
and sometimes those same instruments are the same that we have.
وأحيانا تكون الأدوات المستخدمة هي ذاتها التي نملكها.
They can think in the same way, but they may have a different arrangement,
يمكنها أن تفكر بذات الطريقة، ولكن بترتيب مختلف،
and maybe they're higher in some cases than humans,
وربما تكون يمستوى أعلى من الإنسان في حالات ما،
like long-term memory in a squirrel is actually phenomenal,
كما في الذاكرة طويلة المدى لدى السناجب التي تعتبر مذهلة،
so it can remember where it buried its nuts.
وتتيح لها أن تتذكر أين قامت بتخزين طعامها.
But in other cases they may be lower.
ولكن في حالات أخرى تكون بمستوى أقل.
When we go to make machines,
وعندما نباشر في بناء آلات،
we're going to engineer them in the same way,
فنحن نقوم بتصميمها بالطريقة ذاتها،
where we'll make some of those types of smartness much greater than ours,
حيث نجعل بعض أنواع الذكاء تلك أكثر تقدما من الأنواع التي لدينا نحن،
and many of them won't be anywhere near ours,
وبعضها الآخر يكون بمستوى أدنى بكثير مما لدينا،
because they're not needed.
لأنه لا يوجد حاجة لها.
So we're going to take these things,
وسنقوم بأخذ هذه الأشياء،
these artificial clusters,
هذه المجموعات الصناعية،
and we'll be adding more varieties of artificial cognition to our AIs.
وسنضيف المزيد من أنواع الإدراك الاصطناعي للذكاء الاصطناعي لدينا.
We're going to make them very, very specific.
وسنقوم بجعلها محددة بشكل كبير.
So your calculator is smarter than you are in arithmetic already;
لذا الآلة الحاسبة هي أذكى منك في إجراء العمليات الحسابية،
your GPS is smarter than you are in spatial navigation;
وجهاز تحديد المواقع الجغرافي أذكى منك في الملاحة،
Google, Bing, are smarter than you are in long-term memory.
"جوجل" و"بينج" أذكى منك في الذاكرة طويلة الأمد.
And we're going to take, again, these kinds of different types of thinking
وسوف نأخذ مرة أخرى تلك الأنواع المختلفة من التفكير
and we'll put them into, like, a car.
وسوف نضعها في سيارة مثلا.
The reason why we want to put them in a car so the car drives,
وسبب أننا سنضعها في سيارة لكي تقود نفسها،
is because it's not driving like a human.
بطريقة مختلفة عن قيادة الإنسان.
It's not thinking like us.
وهي لا تفكر كما نفكر نحن.
That's the whole feature of it.
هذه هي الخاصية الأساسية لها.
It's not being distracted,
فهي لا يمكن أن تتشتت،
it's not worrying about whether it left the stove on,
ولن تقلق إن كانت نسيت أن تطفئ الفرن قبل أن تغادر،
or whether it should have majored in finance.
أو أن تفكر أن كان يجب أن تتخصص في المالية.
It's just driving.
هي تقود فقط.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Just driving, OK?
تقود فقط، حسنا؟
And we actually might even come to advertise these
ولربما قمنا بوضع هذا في إعلان
as "consciousness-free."
هي "خالية من الوعي".
They're without consciousness,
فهي خالية من الإدراك،
they're not concerned about those things,
هي لا تهمها تلك الأمور،
they're not distracted.
لا يمكن أن تشتت انتباهها
So in general, what we're trying to do
بشكل عام، ما نحاول القيام به
is make as many different types of thinking as we can.
هو إيجاد أكبر قدر ممكن من أنواع التفكير المختلفة.
We're going to populate the space
سنقوم بمليء الفضاء
of all the different possible types, or species, of thinking.
بجميع الأنواع المتاحة من أشكال الحياة، والتفكير.
And there actually may be some problems
ولربما كانت توجد بعض المشاكل
that are so difficult in business and science
والتي تتميز بصعوبة ما في مجال الأعمال والعلوم
that our own type of human thinking may not be able to solve them alone.
والتي لربما كان تفكيرنا البشري غير قادر على حلها لوحده.
We may need a two-step program,
نحن بحاجة إلى برنامج من خطوتين،
which is to invent new kinds of thinking
لكي يتيح لنا ابتكار أنواع جديدة من التفكير
that we can work alongside of to solve these really large problems,
التي تمكننا من أن نعمل معها لحل تلك المشاكل الكبيرة بالفعل،
say, like dark energy or quantum gravity.
مثل الطاقة المظلمة أو الجاذبية الكمية.
What we're doing is making alien intelligences.
ما نقوم به هو صنع ذكاء من خارج الأرض.
You might even think of this as, sort of, artificial aliens
ويمكن أن تفكر بالأمر ككائنات فضائية اصطناعية
in some senses.
بصورة أو أخرى.
And they're going to help us think different,
وهي ستساعدنا على التفكير بطريقة مختلفة،
because thinking different is the engine of creation
لأن التفكير المختلف هو بمثابة المحرك للابتكار
and wealth and new economy.
والثراء والاقتصاد الجديد.
The second aspect of this is that we are going to use AI
الجانب الثاني لهذا الأمر أننا سنستخدم الذكاء الاصطناعي
to basically make a second Industrial Revolution.
لكي نقوم بإحداث ثورة صناعية ثانية بكل بساطة.
The first Industrial Revolution was based on the fact
الثورة الصناعية الأولى كانت ترتكز على حقيقة
that we invented something I would call artificial power.
أننا اخترعنا شيء أسميه أنا الطاقة الاصطناعية.
Previous to that,
قبل هذا،
during the Agricultural Revolution,
خلال الثورة الزراعية،
everything that was made had to be made with human muscle
كل شيء تتم صناعته كان يجب استخدام العضلات البشرية
or animal power.
أو الطاقة الحيوانية.
That was the only way to get anything done.
كانت تلك هي الطريقة الوحيدة لإنجاز الأعمال.
The great innovation during the Industrial Revolution was,
الاختراع العظيم خلال الثورة الصناعية هو،
we harnessed steam power, fossil fuels,
تمكننا من استخدام طاقة البخار، والوقود الحجري،
to make this artificial power that we could use
لكي نصنع تلك الطاقة الاصطناعية التي يمكننا استخدامها
to do anything we wanted to do.
لكي نقوم بأي شيء نرغب في فعله.
So today when you drive down the highway,
ولذا اليوم عندما تقود خلال الطرق السريعة،
you are, with a flick of the switch, commanding 250 horses --
فأنت ببساطة عندما تدير المفتاح، تتحكم بقوة 250 حصانا
250 horsepower --
250 حصانا
which we can use to build skyscrapers, to build cities, to build roads,
يمكن أن نستخدمها لبناء ناطحات السحاب، أو المدن أو الطرق،
to make factories that would churn out lines of chairs or refrigerators
لإنشاء مصانع يمكننها إنتاج مقاعد وثلاجات
way beyond our own power.
أكثر بكثير مما نقدر عليه لوحدنا.
And that artificial power can also be distributed on wires on a grid
كما يمكن لتلك القوة الصناعية أن توزع من خلال شبكة وأسلاك
to every home, factory, farmstead,
لجميع المنازل والمصانع والمزارع،
and anybody could buy that artificial power,
ويمكن للجميع شراء تلك القوة الصناعية،
just by plugging something in.
بتوصيل شيء ما بتلك الشبكة.
So this was a source of innovation as well,
وقد كان هذا مصدرا للابتكار أيضا،
because a farmer could take a manual hand pump,
حيث يقدر مزارع أن يستخدم مضخة يدوية،
and they could add this artificial power, this electricity,
ويمكنهم إضافة هذه الطاقة الاصطناعية، هذه الكهرباء،
and he'd have an electric pump.
وستتاح له مضخة كهربائية.
And you multiply that by thousands or tens of thousands of times,
ويمكن تكرار الأمر آلاف أو عشرات الألاف من المرات،
and that formula was what brought us the Industrial Revolution.
وهذا الأمر هو ما صنع الثورة الصناعية.
All the things that we see, all this progress that we now enjoy,
جميع ما نراه الآن وكل التطور الذي ننعم به،
has come from the fact that we've done that.
هو ينتج من حقيقة أننا قمنا بذاك الأمر.
We're going to do the same thing now with AI.
سوف نقوم بذات الأمر الآن باستخدام الذكاء الاصطناعي
We're going to distribute that on a grid,
وسوف نقوم بتوزيعه من خلال شبكة توزيع،
and now you can take that electric pump.
ما يمكنك من استخدام مضخات إلكترونية.
You can add some artificial intelligence,
يمكنك أن تضيف القليل من الذكاء الاصطناعي،
and now you have a smart pump.
وسوف ينتج لك مضخة ذكيه.
And that, multiplied by a million times,
وهذا الأمر إن تم تكراره ملايين المرات،
is going to be this second Industrial Revolution.
سينتج عنه تلك الثورة الصناعية الثانية.
So now the car is going down the highway,
الآن السيارة تسير في الطريق السريع،
it's 250 horsepower, but in addition, it's 250 minds.
ولديها 250 حصانا بالإضافة إلى 250 من العقول.
That's the auto-driven car.
هذه هي السيارة ذاتية القيادة.
It's like a new commodity;
إنها بمثابة سلعة جديدة،
it's a new utility.
هذه أداة جديدة.
The AI is going to flow across the grid -- the cloud --
سيتدفق الذكاء الاصطناعي من خلال الشبكة –خدمة السحابة-
in the same way electricity did.
كما يحدث في الشبكة الكهربائية.
So everything that we had electrified,
كل شيء تم استخدام الكهرباء به
we're now going to cognify.
سنجعلها ذات إدراك كذلك.
And I would suggest, then,
سوف أقترح بعد ذلك،
that the formula for the next 10,000 start-ups
أن طريقة البدء في المشاريع 10,000 التالية
is very, very simple,
هي بسيطة جدا جدا
which is to take x and add AI.
وهي أخذ أي شيء ونضيف له ذكاء اصطناعي.
That is the formula, that's what we're going to be doing.
هذه هي الطريقة التي سنقوم بإتباعها واستخدامها.
And that is the way in which we're going to make
هذه هي الطريقة التي سنقوم من خلالها بإحداث
this second Industrial Revolution.
الثورة الصناعية الثانية.
And by the way -- right now, this minute,
بالمناسبة، في هذه اللحظة
you can log on to Google
يمكنك أن تزور "جوجل"
and you can purchase AI for six cents, 100 hits.
وتشتري ذكاء اصطناعي بسعر 6 سنتات، 100 مشاهدة.
That's available right now.
هذا متاح الآن.
So the third aspect of this
والجانب الثالث لهذا الموضوع
is that when we take this AI and embody it,
هو أننا عندما نأخذ هذا الذكاء الاصطناعي ونجسده،
we get robots.
فسوف نحصل على الروبوتات.
And robots are going to be bots,
وستقوم الروبوتات بمهام وحدها،
they're going to be doing many of the tasks that we have already done.
وسوف تؤدي الكثير من المهام التي نقوم بها الآن.
A job is just a bunch of tasks,
العمل عبارة عن سلسلة من المهام،
so they're going to redefine our jobs
ولذا ستقوم بإعادة تعريف أعمالنا
because they're going to do some of those tasks.
لأنها ستقوم بأداء بعض من تلك المهام.
But they're also going to create whole new categories,
كما أنها ستقوم بالإشراف على فئات جديدة بالكامل،
a whole new slew of tasks
مهام جديدة تماماً
that we didn't know we wanted to do before.
لم نكن نعي أننا يجب القيام بها.
They're going to actually engender new kinds of jobs,
سيتولد عنها أنواع جديدة من الأعمال،
new kinds of tasks that we want done,
أنواع جديدة من المهام التي نرغب بالقيام بها،
just as automation made up a whole bunch of new things
كما أن المهام الميكانيكية نتج عنها أشياء جديدة
that we didn't know we needed before,
لم نكن نعرف أننا بحاجة لها من قبل،
and now we can't live without them.
والآن لا يمكننا العيش بدونها.
So they're going to produce even more jobs than they take away,
وهي بذلك ستساهم في إيجاد وظائف أكثر مما ستتسبب في إلغائها،
but it's important that a lot of the tasks that we're going to give them
والضروري أن تكون معظم المهام التي سنوكلها لهم
are tasks that can be defined in terms of efficiency or productivity.
هي مهام يمكن تحديدها من حيث الكفاءة أو الإنتاجية.
If you can specify a task,
إن أمكنك تحديد مهمة ما،
either manual or conceptual,
إما يدويا أو نظرياً،
that can be specified in terms of efficiency or productivity,
والتي يمكن تحديدها من وجهة نظر كفاءة أو إنتاجية،
that goes to the bots.
التي تذهب إلى الروبوتات.
Productivity is for robots.
الإنتاجية هي شيء للروبوتات.
What we're really good at is basically wasting time.
نحن بكل بساطة متميزون في إضاعة الوقت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We're really good at things that are inefficient.
نحن جيدون جدا في تأدية الأشياء الغير فعالة.
Science is inherently inefficient.
العلم هو غير كفؤ بطبيعته.
It runs on that fact that you have one failure after another.
فهو مبنى أساساً على حقيقة الفشل مرة تلو الأخرى.
It runs on the fact that you make tests and experiments that don't work,
هو مبنى على أساس أنك تجري اختبارات وتجارب غير ناجحة،
otherwise you're not learning.
وإلا فإنك لن تتعلم.
It runs on the fact
هو مبنى على أساس
that there is not a lot of efficiency in it.
عدم وجود كفاءة كبيرة به.
Innovation by definition is inefficient,
الابتكار يحمل في تعريفه عدم الكفاءة،
because you make prototypes,
لأنك تصنع النماذج الأولية،
because you try stuff that fails, that doesn't work.
لأنك تجرب الأشياء التي تفشل ولا تؤدي عملها.
Exploration is inherently inefficiency.
الاستكشاف هو غير كفؤ بطبيعته.
Art is not efficient.
الفن لا يتسم بالكفاءة.
Human relationships are not efficient.
العلاقات البشرية لا تتسم بالكفاءة.
These are all the kinds of things we're going to gravitate to,
هذه جميعها أشياء سننجذب لها،
because they're not efficient.
لأنها تتميز بعدم الكفاءة.
Efficiency is for robots.
الكفاءة هي متاحة للروبوتات فقط.
We're also going to learn that we're going to work with these AIs
كما أننا سنتعلم العمل مع أنواع الذكاء الاصطناعي،
because they think differently than us.
لأنها تفكر بطريقة مختلفة عنا.
When Deep Blue beat the world's best chess champion,
عندما تغلب "ديب بلو" على بطل العالم في الشطرنج،
people thought it was the end of chess.
اعتقد الناس أنها نهاية الشطرنج.
But actually, it turns out that today, the best chess champion in the world
لكن في الحقيقة، اتضح أن بطل الشطرنج الأفضل في العالم
is not an AI.
هو ليس ذكاء اصطناعيا.
And it's not a human.
كما أنه ليس بشريا.
It's the team of a human and an AI.
لكنه فريق مكون من إنسان وذكاء اصطناعي.
The best medical diagnostician is not a doctor, it's not an AI,
أفضل التشخيصات الطبية لا يجريها طبيب، وليس ذكاء اصطناعي،
it's the team.
ولكن فريق.
We're going to be working with these AIs,
سوف نعمل مع أنواع الذكاء الاصطناعي،
and I think you'll be paid in the future
وأعتقد أننا سوف نتسلم راتبنا في المستقبل
by how well you work with these bots.
بناء على مدى قدرتنا على العمل معها.
So that's the third thing, is that they're different,
وهذا هو الأمر الثالث، أنها مختلفة عنا،
they're utility
فهي أدوات مساعدة
and they are going to be something we work with rather than against.
وستكون أشياء نحن نعمل معها عوضا أن نكون نعمل ضدها.
We're working with these rather than against them.
سنعمل جنبا إلى جنب بدل أن نكون ضدهم.
So, the future:
ولذا، في المستقبل،
Where does that take us?
إلى أين سيؤدي بنا هذا؟
I think that 25 years from now, they'll look back
أعتقد أن الناس بعد 25 عاماً من الآن سينظرون لوقتنا الحالي
and look at our understanding of AI and say,
وينظرون إلى مفهومنا عن الذكاء الاصطناعي وسيقولون،
"You didn't have AI. In fact, you didn't even have the Internet yet,
"ليس لديكم ذكاء اصطناعي، في الحقيقة لم يكن لديكم إنترنت بعد،
compared to what we're going to have 25 years from now."
مقارنة بما هو لدينا بعد 25 سنة من الآن"
There are no AI experts right now.
لا يوجد خبراء في الذكاء الاصطناعي الآن.
There's a lot of money going to it,
الكثير من المال ينفق في هذا المجال،
there are billions of dollars being spent on it;
ويتم إنفاق المليارات من الدولارات لتطويره،
it's a huge business,
أنه مجال عمل ضخم جداً،
but there are no experts, compared to what we'll know 20 years from now.
لكن لا يوجد خبراء، مقارنة بما سنعرفه بعد 20 سنة من الآن.
So we are just at the beginning of the beginning,
لذا نحن ببساطة في بداية البداية،
we're in the first hour of all this.
نحن في الساعات الأولى من هذا العصر.
We're in the first hour of the Internet.
نحن في الساعات الأولى من عمر الإنترنت.
We're in the first hour of what's coming.
نحن في الساعات الأولى لما هو آت.
The most popular AI product in 20 years from now,
المنتج المبني على الذكاء الاصطناعي والذي سيكون الأكثر انتشارا بعد 20 سنة،
that everybody uses,
والذي سيستخدمه الجميع،
has not been invented yet.
لم يتم اختراعه بعد.
That means that you're not late.
وهذا يعني أنكم لستم متأخرين عن موعدكم.
Thank you.
شكرا جزيلاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)